Guide to the Bruce Davidson Photograph Collection 1957-2001 PR 89
New-York Historical Society
Bruce Davidson photograph collection
1957-2001
New-York Historical Society
Davidson, Bruce, 1933-
PR 89
10 Linear feet in 6 boxes of various size, and 3 oversize folders
The Bruce Davidson Photograph Collection consists of about 400 photographs taken by Bruce Davidson, an American photographer whose work is often focused on the relationship between people and place. The photographs were taken between 1957 and 2001.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bruce Davidson, 2001. Gift of anonymous donor, 2018.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Scope and Content Note
The Bruce Davidson Photograph Collection consists of about 400 photographs taken by Bruce Davidson, an American photographer whose work is often focused on the relationship between people and place. The collection is arranged into two series.
Series I: East 100th Street consists of 14 images from Davidson's photo project of the same name. These photos were taken between 1966 and 1968 in the neighborhood of East Harlem in New York City.They document street activity, and particularly focus on children. The modern photographic prints are produced from the vintage negatives and signed on the verso by the photographer. These photographs were donated by the artist in 2001.
Series II: Photo Projects contains 394 images from over 20 of Davidson's photo projects undertaken between 1957 and 2001. These photographs were donated by an anonymous donor in 2018.
Photos in this series come from Davidson's projects documenting the 50th anniversary of the U.S. Air Force; the Civil Rights movement in the U.S., including the 1965 Selma March; street life in Chicago in 1989; a circus; the streets and gardens of Paris; and English, Scottish and Welsh towns. In addition, there are portraits of Isaac Bashevis Singer, a Polish-American writer in Yiddish.
Also included are selections from Davidson's projects that focus on various aspects of life in New York City: a 1950s teenage gang from Brooklyn; children at the American Museum of Natural History in 1960; the subway in the 1980s; Central Park in the 1990s; the construction of the Verrazzano Bridge in 1963-1964; New York Harbor, including the South Street Seaport, the Statue of Liberty, the shoreline, boats, ships, dock workers and ship crew members; and the Lower East Side from the 1950s-1990s.
This series also includes photographs from the East 100th Street photo essay that comprises Series I, along with images from Davidson's 1998 project which revisits the same East Harlem neighborhood and explores the changes that occurred over intervening 30 years.
Biographical / Historical
Bruce Davidson (1933-) is an American photographer known for his photo essays documenting people and places with sensitivity and sympathy. His photographs capture moments and details that reveal the complexity of his subjects.
Davidson studied photography at the Rochester Institute of Technology and the School of Design of Yale University. He has been a member of the Magnum Photos agency since 1958. His photographs, notably those taken in Harlem, New York City, have been widely exhibited and published.
Davidson's first published project was "East 100th Street" (1970), a book of 123 photographs of the inhabitants of a single block in East Harlem in New York City. Other books featuring his photographs include "Subsistence U.S.A." (1973), with text by Carol Hill, "Bruce Davidson Photographs" (1978), "Subway" (1986), "Central Park" (1995), and "In Color" (2014).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series based on donor and date of acquisition. The first series consists of 14 images from Davidson's photo project "East 100th Street" donated by the artist in 2001.
The second series contains 394 images from over 20 of Davidson's photo projects. These photographs were donated by an anonymous donor in 2018.
Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Chicago (Ill.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works; East Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Gang members; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); New York Harbor (N.Y. and N.J.); One-hundredth Street (New York, N.Y.); Verrazano-Narrows Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Gelatin silver prints.; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-1991
- Series I: East 100th Street, 1966-1968; 19384
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of fourteen images taken between 1966 and 1968 in the neighborhood of East Harlem in New York City. They document street activity and people inside their homes, and particularly focus on children. These prints were donated by Bruce Davidson in 2002.
  - [Waterfront Family and Hammock], 1966-1968; 19398 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Children Looking Through Window with Chicken Wire], 1966-1968; 19397 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Boy on Rooftop With Kite], 1966-1968; 19396 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Girl on Couch with View of E. 100th Street], 1966-1968; 19395 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Facade], 1966-1968; 19394 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Women Seated Laughing], 1966-1968; 19393 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Couple Dancing at Jukebox], 1966-1968; 19392 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Woman in Kitchen with Madonna on Wall], 1966-1968; 19391 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Boy With Pigeon], 1966-1968; 19390 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Woman Holding Newborn], 1966-1968; 19389 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Girls Playing Jump rope at Night], 1966-1968; 19388 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Group outside Atena's Grocery], 1966-1968; 19387 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Two Children Seated on Fire Escape], 1966-1968; 19386 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Reflection of Man sitting at Restaurant Counter], 1966-1968; 19385 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Photo Projects, 1957-2001
  This series contains 394 images from over 20 of Davidson's photo essays undertaken between 1957 and 2001. The focus is most often on the people in the photographs, though there are some scenic images of places such as Paris, Central Park, and New York Harbor.
  Photos in this series come from Davidson's projects documenting the 50th anniversary of the U.S. Air Force; the Civil Rights movement in the U.S., including the 1965 Selma March; street life in Chicago in 1989; a circus; the streets and gardens of Paris; and English, Scottish and Welsh towns. In addition, there are portraits of Isaac Bashevis Singer, a Polish-American writer in Yiddish.
  Also included are selections from Davidson's projects that focus on various aspects of life in New York City: a 1950s teenage gang from Brooklyn; children at the American Museum of Natural History in 1960; the subway in the 1980s; Central Park in the 1990s; the construction of the Verrazzano Bridge in 1963-1964; New York Harbor, including the South Street Seaport, the Statue of Liberty, the shoreline, boats, ships, dock workers and ship crew members; and the Lower East Side from the 1950s-1990s.
  This series also includes photographs from the East 100th Street photo essay that comprises Series I, along with images from Davidson's 1998 project which revisits the same East Harlem neighborhood and explores the changes that occurred over intervening 30 years.
  - Air Force, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chicago, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Circus, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - England, Scotland and Wales, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - France - Paris, 1957-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - France - Paris, 1957-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New York - American Museum of Natural History, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - New York - Broadway Islands, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York - Brooklyn Bridge, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - New York - Brooklyn Gang, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New York - Brooklyn Gang, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - New York - Cafeteria, 1973 (Folder FF1)
    1 photo, 37x37. An older couple eating at a cafeteria on the Lower East Side.
  - New York - Central Park, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New York - Central Park, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New York - Central Park, 1992 (Folder FF2)
    2 photos, 21x41
  - New York - Columbia University, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New York - East 100th Street, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - New York - East 100th Street, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - New York - East Harlem Revisited, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - New York - Harbor, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - New York - Harbor, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - New York - Lower East Side, 1957-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - New York - Lower East Side, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New York - Subway, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New York - Subway, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - New York - The Tombs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York - Verrazzano Bridge, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New York - Verrazzano Bridge, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - New York - Verrazzano Bridge, 1964 (Folder FF3)
    1 photo, 40x60
  - New York - World Trade Center, 1986-2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Portraits - Isaac Singer, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Portraits - Isaac Singer, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Times of Change: Civil Rights Movement, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)